I was speaking to a friend recently
about seclusion and what I was saying
was that seclusion is neither good not
bad but it's really what you do inside
seclusion that makes it makes it sir and
we're speaking about more of it if your
mind is defiled then it's not seclusion
it's not gonna make it better
you know seclusion is it's like can
amplify amplify whatever you carry
whatever you have so that's why you're
trying to determine where the seclusion
is good or bad he's trying to determine
whether amplification is good or bad but
in itself that neutral amplification is
neither good nor bad but things they
trampling fire will determine it whether
it's good or bad whether you're
amplifying bad states of mind or are you
amplifying the holsombach
the good ones so seclusion that's all
that's all it is really it will only
increase what you already have
that's why the Buddha himself said the
person needs to be ready first
restrained by the rules of Patti maca
developed mine in Samadhi develop the
right view before that person can
benefit from solitude there doesn't mean
you shouldn't be trying to develop
solitude and because that's another way
to find out whether you are carrying
good or bad mostly which you serve in
seclusion and you see what gets
amplified and then you lose okay now the
bad states are amplify which I must
address that I mustn't develop a view or
will never go to seclusion again because
it amplified all these bad things know
it amplify things that you need to do so
from that point of your seclusion is
always good good as an indicator of what
work needs to be done in to what extent
so sometimes you don't notice things you
go into seclusion and it will amplify
whatever it's really there fundamentally
underlying your mood and so on and once
it's amplified you know it's there you
can almost see where you're going in
your life absolutely responsibility
you're trying to avoid in your life so
amplification is good but not in itself
it's good if you is rightly if used
skillfully to highlight the symptoms
that you're trying to discern so in that
sense solitude yeah it's necessary but
in itself solitude does not result with
or any development if you don't make the
effort to develop and undo on awesome
States very good to challenge yourself
absolutely good strike if you don't if
you don't challenge if you don't
challenge your situation you're not
gonna see what's underlying you and
that's the people think challenging
situation means exposing yourself to
sensuality and temptations know that
basically proliferating your ignorance
challenging situation is please
practicing with drama because a
seclusion boredom anxiety of solitude
and loneliness that's why you start
changing the basically the fundamental
structure will experience not just a
particular issue that you might be
bothered or you're trying to overcome so
you want to amplify it you want to put
put a magnifying glass and then see what
shows and then you know exactly where
your work is so in that sense you use
solitude rightly even with the wrong
view even without you know having
developed right view and in jhanas in
Samadhi and so on you can still do solid
to your advantage but it obviously
is gonna be unpleasant but that's the
whole point
if I'm doing unwholesome state states is
is is totally Pleasant everybody will be
another
because everyone will just follow
pleasure the resulting erection so if
your mind is most of the time lustful
most of the time angry most of time
distracted you go into seclusion for a
few days it might not be those things
quite novelty experience beautiful
instant the more you close the daughter
you're alone
everything gets amplified sometimes but
but no no that's yeah settle in
seclusion and then you see what's that
gobbling up from the bottom but that's
another thing see if you if you never
amplify even unwholesome stage you never
realize how serious they are how how
deeply rooted those issues are and
that's people by default people who are
not interested in practice that's why
nobody likes solitude everybody tries to
find constantly something to keep their
mind occupied something to keep them
flowing on the surface because
fundamentally what solitude will amplify
is the unpleasant state of existence
unpleasant unpleasant recognition you
don't necessarily fully grasp with a
fully admitted to the matter are you
certainly start getting hints of that
fundamental lack of control in regard to
your feelings in regard to your
existence in regard to life in regard to
everything you hold dear to you that's
why it's solid should often results in
what first boredom then their boredom
becomes existential dread
and the Buddha
so Buddhist encourages people for monks
not to go into seclusion maybe for long
periods unless they've got a grasp
yeah situation on their minds can handle
but that doesn't mean that you should
spend most of your day occupied with
others or just being physically present
with others no you shouldn't go to the
complete wilderness you're gonna be
fearing for your life and what most wild
seclusion - finally it will be too much
to handle but that's not to say oh you
should you should you should socialize
no quite the opposite so unless you
prepare yourself so that kind of
seclusion with lesser amounts of
seclusion you'll never prepare yourself and that
you'll never prepare yourself and that
that's the problem you said before where
people try to determine the environment
the circumstances whether it's whether
that will do the practice for you so a
seclusion good or is seclusion bad it
depends while you do it
it depends what Chapel if it depends
whether you're ignoring where you're at
what you're amplifying but if people
don't see that then they light the blame
seclusion or frames pray seclusion for
wrong reasons so I went to too much in
too much seclusion too much soon my mind
couldn't handle it so I developer view
seclusion is bad and now I don't do it
and there's absolutely no reason to
develop that view
that was you overdoing it based on a bad
experience but if you start discerning
and realize well it's just an amplifier
here amplified my bad states of mind so
verify as the pool would send the suit
as a wise man would reflect thus what if
I were to undo my unwholesome states or
at least suppress them to some degree to
my mindfulness and discernment and
effort and virtue and then I try
seclusion and then the Buddha said there
will be absolute bliss and pleasure
pleasure of seclusion the joy that
nothing else can match but it needs to
be developed in a manner
because it's so that people leave
themselves out of the equation
while judging please know the seclusion
is bad yeah because of you yeah that's
what I mean the obviously isn't natural
tendency in everyone to develop a
factual view that pertains to factual
seemingly factual state of things as a
universal independent Albany it's a fact
has nothing to do with me but we comes
to practice of Dhamma most of the things
will be determined
we're bye bye where your intentions are
rooted that's what makes it good or bad
not universal rule as I said you can you
know you can go on a meditation retreat
for a completely utterly unwholesome
wrong reasons but on paper meditation is
always good but you don't get to avoid
your solid to void practice to avoid
responsibility so if that form in there
are obvious things that are always bad
and that's where the pieces come in you
just never do those things but now
everything else that's more refined than
that will be determined by your
intentions as I gave the example before
multiple times like oh I want to go to
the library read the sutras like if you
say that like that it's so it's a good
thing isn't it it's great but if you
like start looking at it why you want to
do it because there's like lots of
people there and you're gonna end up
socializing maybe even meet like-minded
people and and like you don't
necessarily explicitly think about it
that's the nature of inauthentic
attitude in bad faith you turn a blind
eye to for yourself to yourself to what
the real reason is and what the real
reason is that I want to go to such and
such place and read the sutras into
meditation well it's really because I
feel a bit odd or a bit lonely or a bit
scared or a bit this little bit that I
need distraction that's all always the
reason so when there is not a reason
then if the reason is genuine or I want
to find all these suitors I spent three
days thinking about it
that's now means okay it's a good good
reason good thing that's why I like the
things that are unavoidable like things
that are that you can do without such as
with a said sexual intercourse of
sensuality you just you do it out you
just stop doing it but things that you
can't do it out such as eating food that
will be determined that's not always
unwholesome even if it's the food you
really like it's unwholesome if you eat
it carelessly which means if you eat it
for the wrong reasons if you eat it with
the reasons of carelessness means
automatically you'll be needing it for
the reasons of sensual enjoyment not for
the genuine factual hunger so it's your
responsibility then to reroute your
reasons in the right foundation of
hunger sustenance of the body basic
health and strength so that you can
carry on slightly harder lifestyle of
solitude and some Stoli chicken practice
the Dharma but if you forget those
reasons then you automatically them sent
for central reasons but if you don't
look at the reasoning then you'll be
blaming the food then you'll be trying
to avoid the taste or blaming the taste
or not eating or fast no luck Giants
starve yourself to death thinking that's
the ultimate renunciation but that's not
the point
so things like food and the many other
things they are not in themselves
neither horsin around also they're a
necessity but that doesn't mean that oh
they're a necessity
I can either carelessly know by eating
it carelessly you make the necessity
unwholesome so the responsibility for
wholesome wholesome lies where your
intentions are that's why every
intention every action is intentional
it's rooted in intention so good action
bad action neutral action will be so
based on good bad or neutral intentions
but it's easier to sort of develop of
review and try to make it factual and
just blame things or make things
responsible for your attentions oh no I
am hungry I must eat that's true
malleable but if you eat carelessly
means your hunger will be secondary to
your sensual enjoyment of their food
if you'd carefully
I mean central and Roman will be
secondary to your hunger which means
even as the Buddha said even if it's the
various choices of various car is Hank
the grunts it still won't be infusing
your mind with sensuality because you
haven't lost perspective you're eating
mindfully aware transparent to both the
reasons for your eating and you become
transparent by dwelling with those
reasons by not turning a blind eye
that's the whole point so we're going to
seclusion for example yet that's the
right reasons you clarify the reasons if
you're not sure whether they're right or
wrong well go a little bit and then see
what comes up now why am i doing it
exactly but if you if you can't handle
seclusion okay you go back but not so I
all never try this again I can't handle
not because seclusion is at fault I
can't handle because my mind is at fault
because I'm not stronger there was so
I'll then practice and develop more
strength so that I can handle it
it's not optional that's the thing
amplifying the foundations of your mind
to seclusion is not optional but yeah
and the amplification can be bad as well
if you haven't done that city work
before
you stated your mind is more it's much
more clearer
there's no one's around is nothing
taking away your attention and by not
being distracted in that like basic
manner what you're gonna stay with is
the state of your mind
which means whether you want it or not
you're gonna start seeing them more
clearly and that's what the Buddha said
one cannot develop the sign of his own
mind chipton emitter without having
chipton emitter without having
established himself in seclusion and
without having developed a sign with the
mind sheet an emitter walk how come and
develop the right view that's impossible
so in that sense that something like
amplification is not optional but well
my practice is so good I can do without
solitude no practice in solitude are
almost similar practice is amplifying
these things that need to be undone
amplifying wrong views because of which
you get to abandon them
means if you start getting angry in
solitude yep because of whatever you
thought you're having you're getting
angry you can then see exactly what you
do about that absolute like what would
say it shows where you at how do I deal
with anger
yeah well the boundaries the lines you
cross from your mental thought of anger
to a verbal expression of anger to
physical expression of anger are much
clearer in solitude you realize that
actually there is no connection between
the three there it's not that thought
automatically seeps into speech didn't
automatically seeps into physical action
no thought always remains within domain
of thought speech always remains within
the main speech bodily action always
remain within the main body action they
are they're completely separate domain
unaware of each other you can sell them
three simultaneous domains of your three
types of intentions but it's thought
with ignorance goes for speech goes for
the physical action but you your
ignorance is that bridge that they
connect say nothing else and when you
live in the environment that revolves
around it it's automatic
I think bad I speak that I'm angry I say
it is just effortless it's with the
grain so to speak but in the solitude
pace that's kind of you can benefit from
if you start practicing that restraint
of bodily action verbal action then you
get to see that mental action stays on
the level of mind even if you ever
thought I'm gonna go and say something
then you go and say something saying
something and thinking something of two
simultaneous things present together but
not the same it's not the same thing
channeled from thoughts into a speech
and action it's your magical belief that
connects them your assumption pretty
much you're wrong wrong view you Rupa
done
but in solitude that boundary of you
crossing it magically my thought means
my speech means my action becomes more
apparent and you lose your own belief in
it that's what people need to believe in
their own anger in order to act angry
you need to make that leap angry
thoughts cannot make you punch somebody
or say something bad
it's your carelessness in regards to the
angry thoughts that make you develop
belief that punching or saying something
offensive is how this is expressed
that's why the more you give in to anger
the more of the ways of expressing it
proliferate which means the easier was
going to be to express it in that
magical belief many but if you start
straining your belief of expressing the
anger through a physical action you
realize yeah I'm angry mentally but what
does happen what does that have to do
with me harming this lump of flesh in
this body has nothing to do with it I
need to believe that he has something to
do with it that's why people saw this
with a gang with a break
in enemy things because the belief of
anger has been so proliferated did yeah
for them now the things almost become
like other people that they can harm
through their anger and effect but then
it's futile you know it's futile but you
can't help it
so you smash up thing that upsets you it
takes that magical conjoined anger
out yeah you do you have no other means
of dealing with it yeah with the
unpleasantness of anger exactly the only
means were given and try to follow that
way and then that makes you follow it
further and further and further but
there is no end to that
it's infinite infinite proliferation of
your expression but nothing can uproot
it because it's all secondary to the
reason for your expressing it in the
first place so one is overcome by anger
if you're shouting yeah
so what about sadness say in seclusion
there is just sadness sad mind of any
mental state if you do anything by body
or by a speech means you couldn't you
could not have contained it you were too
weak to contain it so you gave in to the
magical belief of expressing it through
this other separate domains but what's
the clarity of that becomes apparent
that these domains disconnected in a way
you you become unable to believe in
expressing your anger or your sadness
so you can't be angry nor can you cry
shout shout shout just becomes
disconnected that's why the Buddha when
he was describing the nature of the
speech he said having thought it
pondered having taught him pondered one
breaks into speech he doesn't say having
thought and pondered then those thoughts
and wanders like flow into the speech
that comes out there is no connection
thinking and pondering breaking into
speech but two separate domains but yeah
you must have thinking in pondering you
know the domain of speech to be broken
and spoken but they don't connect
certainly not in your assumed way of
directionality of with the grain I think
I speak I do ruin be automatically what
is uniting for Buddha Jeana doing
speaking and thinking is his sense of
self so the more you will do the sense
of self the freer from action three
types of action you become hence the end
end of kama and direction for Inara
because there is nothing connecting
these three type selection
ignorant so we thought there would be
only the thought in spoken alone would
be the spoken in done there all be able
to done that's it so it's a overcome
with sadness to say you're quite aware
of that thought I mean so if you try to
get rid of it
evening arms try I don't understand this
I'm suffering in accountable I don't
want it anyway if you try to do anything
when I can't do it but if there is
sadness and you've understood the nature
of sadness then you wouldn't have well
you wouldn't even you wouldn't even be
able to consider giving in to the
pressure and looking for the ways of
doing something about it because you're
not affected by it in the first place
all expressing it that's women doing
something about it means expressing it
people express it because that presents
itself as a way of doing something about
it
and it's not incidental that people have
a view or you must not repress your
feelings because they'll find a way out
as if you give in so badly at one point
could you be trying to restrain yourself
right yes sure you will amplify the
pressure of giving in but that's the
whole point
because your knowledge should be the
thing that cuts everything the knowledge
knowledge knowledge the full
understanding of the recent phenomena
whatever the phenomena may be sadness
anger whatever makes you not affected by
it in the first place that's the true
laying down the burden there is no
burden of duty there is no burden of I
must do this summons do that I must
avoid it when it arises I must go this
way when it comes this woman's go that
way I must manage it all of that becomes
redundant is you're not affected by it
in the first minutes because you're
looking at it that's a true freedom
relief like oh it doesn't touch me this
we used to touch me it doesn't touch me
anymore I don't need to do anything but
I don't need to watch my breath I don't
you do anything because I fully
understood it and I'm not affected by in
the first place and I have no doubt
about it I means okay dead lack of
clarity regarding whether you affected
by it or not affect you so you're
affected by so honestly transparently
you admit continue you go further in
your discernment in your reflection
until and we reflect about what may be
but if I were affected wouldn't suffer
yes don't suffer No so in this
particular case at least I'm not a thing
because there's no suffering no there is
any pressure to do something about this
it's just there literally okay will not
be affected I'm not sure well let's keep
a close eye on to see so then it comes
up well maybe maybe but big bit less bit
more and you keep reflecting you keep
not ignoring the debts with the problem
is the problem is not that you don't
know how to deal with it who you haven't
dealt with it quickly enough we haven't
dealt with it properly enough or
skillfully the problem is that you need
to deal with it in the first place so
you want to find a place but you don't
have to deal with anything but that
place is not physically found on top of
mountain or something that place can
only be found internally but nothing
with no internal arising feelings none
of them can touch you none of them can
affect you without you needing to deny
them without you needing to indulge them
without you needing to ignored
means feeling is there fully reason what
if it rises more doesn't matter can
arise to the infinite amount
no the main of feeling can affect you
thus doesn't matter the intensity you
don't worry about intensity because you
know you're free from the domain where
this intensity is manifested in the
nature so whether it's like I don't know
something is significant like whether
it's something insignificant like a bad
day and you couldn't do things you
wanted or whether it you're dying parent
in front of you doesn't matter the
intensity of displeasure you're not
affected by it because you abandon the
domain of it you understood the domain
of it which means abandoned well
everything then has to arise through you
view through the lens of what is right
you see everything the widest point
where things manifest so from there
they're just gonna be more and more
particular but either why this point has
been understood the basis of feeling as
pleasant unpleasant neutral so you use
you stop you're not concerned with it
with the content of this is Pleasant
this is unpleasant you concern with the
fact that it's being felt in the first
place that's what sariputra meant what
Evers felt counts as suffering counts as
a problem counts is something that needs
to be undone and overcome doesn't matter
what it's felt there was the right view
whatever is experienced yeah the right
view means that overcoming whatever's
felt that that means that whatever it's
felt in the content cannot affect you
either cuz you're not affected by the
feeling in itself let alone pleasant
unpleasant a neutral manifestation of
that feeling once you're in seclusion
you can also start to see lust arising
from a great great distance oh yes Oh
hatred of Isaac my greatest even before
he crosses the horizon yeah where before
it should sneak up on you and just take
over yeah now you can see it just they
always have to come the same way the
only way so that means that the only way
they can come is if you ignore them if
you know that it always comes this way
it always manifest itself from distance
it's not getting closer and closer and
closer it will get too close to you when
you can't do anything about it it's
because you've been looking away
that's why distraction I delusion isn't
is pretty much the basis of
proliferation for lost ensign and under
anyway that was the most plain water
you haven't been ignoring it means you
cannot come that close because it
requires you to not look at it in order
to come to you because the if you see
distraction you can see the understand
destruction you can see what is
connected to what is a tester and down
the line yeah you see what else comes
through it yeah and you see all those
things yes so so that's what mindfulness
you can't have too much of and it's it's
it's always to be practice you see what
you're not overdue mindful you can't
overdo not ignoring you can overdo
active thinking about this so you can
overdo non active thinking about this
but you can't overdo does that awareness
and recognition of what's present you
can't undo that you can't overdo that
do you start to sense what's connected
with unwholesome what's a picking up the
tokens in the science the periphery
what are the indicators of this
typically see the connections become
more apparent obvious yeah oh
when horizon changes that is I end up
doing such and such things out of
sensuality and you know you see when you
ignoring it then you just find yourself
doing this unwholesome things but not
because they're inevitably to be done as
I said even if it's a total sensuality
manifested owner on a mental level you
are the one with your own central
assumption they then crosses into verbal
and physical domain there is no natural
flow between these domains that's what
you are always responsible for
directions because action requires
crossing from that domain thoughts of
sensuality are not your action they
manifest themselves but you entertaining
indulging welcoming adding more to it
acting physically verbally out of it
that's your action so that's why no
amount of external circumstances will
ever be responsible for you choosing to
act certain way because in the most
fundamental sense you yourself and
nobody else he is responsible for that
belief the travels from the domain of
thought to the domain of speech to the
domain of physical action there is no
connection between them this only you
believe this is Who I am
so you could say having thought upon the
one breaks into speech one breaks into
action because of his own wrong guilt
because of his own views him is affected
by greed aversion and ignorance
and that's why wherever whatever you do
you remain bound as the owner of that
action as the Buddha would say because
you are the you are the bridge between
thought and speech and and the physical
act you remove that bridge then
literally just have things manifested in
physical domain things manifested in
mental domain things managed invested in
verbal domain prompted by significance
there is no basis for an awesome anymore
because because that bridge has been
undone so having an angry thought
doesn't mean that automatically you're
going to shout exactly do something now
you may need to break into shouting you
need to choose to do it you need to give
in to it even if it feels the most
natural thing there is no it feels the
most natural effortless thing is cuz
you've never been practicing enough
restraint about it so you've been
smoothing the way basically when you
missing the groove of that particular
expression but it didn't have to be
greased that way which means you can
undo it you know if you keep checking
the wall to the same way down the hill
it's gonna make a little little trench
all the way down eventually and the more
you do it the bigger the trench becomes
in the end you can just pour it gently
if you go down the trench you don't even
have to throw it
but nomads of depth of the trench will
make any difference if there is no water
being poured on it in the first place if
you're not affected by angry thoughts
there will be no ways of looking for
expression whether established way of
expressing the anger or new ways of
expressing the area there is no anger as
if there is no need to express these
arisen thoughts means all these things
all these channels and trenches they've
been made through my careless behavior
in the past a dead dried-up side like a
palm stop cutted its root so you don't
go and trim around the branches or try
to cover up level the trenches that your
anger dargah no just stop fueling stop
feeding it with the water it will dry up
doesn't matter how many trenches stay
what matters is water running down them
or not so you don't go trim it on the
branches you are bruited then all the branches
you are bruited then all the branches
are dried up and they're done that's the
nature proliferation branching out
creating trenches of expression and so
on so you're trying to deal with that
means you know dealing with that which
cause that you don't dealing with a
problem you're trying to address the
symptoms the problem is you not being
able to overcome the need for expression
of your action manifested own mental
level with the speech with your body
like no more essential thoughts can
result a new physically performing
centrality only you can result in you
physically performing sensuality on
account of being pressured by the
central thoughts but again no amount of
pressure can automatically make you do
it pressure can make you decide to do it
and give in to the magical belief that
this is how sensuality can be expressed
or satisfied and that's why you can have
a satisfied because it's separate
domains thought and desire from one
domain your physical satisfaction
scratching edges could really separate
me and you would want that our
sensuality is opah Donna it's an
assumption taking it to be that which it isn't
taking it to be that which it isn't
you take physical domain to be that
expression of the mental domain but the
two separate domains as I said unaware
of each other
nothing to do with each other it's
thought and physical action you are the
one who makes them connect so to speak
they can't really connect that's what
freedom from sensuality is possible in
the first place if they were truly
connectable means yeah you could truly
satisfy your desires they manifest on
the level of the thinking things could
be released but it requires belief
Madonna is almost is a form of belief
that's why belief in a virtue and duty
bill self view like a belief believing
that there is a new pen itself belief of
sensuality you believe that that's your
sensuality is in that physical domain
but it's your thought and desire that's
what's in childhood so if you stop if
you start this training which means you
prevent the habit of that expression of
it along the physical lines in the
physical domain you will stop feeding
that wrong belief and then become
apparent there is a thought of
sensuality and in itself that's already
enclosed that's already finished it's a
phenomenon of desire but that meaning I
now go and do this and get pursue this
food or this person whatever I want it's
a completely separate thing that only
your magical belief united as one
leading to the other and that's why it's
irreversible as well once that becomes
apparent you cannot then reintroduce
that magical belief only ignoring it
makes you enables you to maintain the
connection between the two is the reason
a connection so ignoring that there is
no connection that's how you maintain
the connection
[Music]